[SPEAKER_00]: So, would you say that the Sotāpanna is perfectly self-transparent?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that way is the Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view is basically self-transparency?
[SPEAKER_00]: To the sufficient extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the culmination of... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the art of complete culmination is arahantship, when there's absolutely no contradiction left within you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's what Buddha meant by the little dust in their eyes, more dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is basically transparent means you see through clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing obscuring.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not as transparent, you have some dust in your eyes, so you cannot quite see clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's someone with a little bit of dust in their eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means they could still hear him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They could still recognize what he was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the ones with a little dust in their eyes, yeah, they would need just
[SPEAKER_01]: Fewer prompts towards that... oh, developing that transparency, that recognition of the certain universal principles, understanding those, understanding the nature of things, to the fundamental, to their own existence, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing else that's being obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have those with more dust in their eyes, they need to invest more effort into developing their transparency.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, really, the question is what transparency is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does somebody... What is self-transparency?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, see, there is... developing self-transparency is a thread of practice, of effort, that is in common to somebody who is patujana and somebody who is even ādi-asāvaka.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if Puthujjana starts to develop self-transparency, he's heading towards the right view, even if he doesn't necessarily know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The extent of his transparency is sort of... that's what's in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: At least the idea of the direction that that's worth developing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why some people in the suttas, when they met the Buddha, literally just heard one sentence from him and became fully enlightened, because they've actually
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like... that's the kind of... that's the basis of the Buddha's teaching, the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to... if you're interested in practicing according to what the Buddha was talking about, then it's all within this idea of becoming transparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding your motives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was going to ask you that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what...
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the definition of transparent and non-transparent?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would be a different characteristic of it, that you could differentiate these two things?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody who's transparent has... is clear about their motives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, transparent in regard to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Transparent in regard to motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Motivation for what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, motivation for bodily action, for verbal action, for mental action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the entire teaching is bound and contained within that nature of action and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What am I doing?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not transparent in regard to such and such thing that I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the transparency we talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's transparency in regard to your own present, here and now, pretty much, whatever you're doing, thinking, saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Transparency in regard to motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the most encompassing general way you could describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of like... could you say it's like... yes, it's not being clear about everything, but just being... Far from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Far from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But just being... because there are things that are not clear, that's their nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's being clear about the direction you're heading in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's being cleared.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about being clear about actions you're intending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're about to intend actions you intended.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's just the kind of vague direction of those actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in maths, I say vague.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be... you might not be able to... Like I say, not everything is clear, but you just know that this direction is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, like, shall I do this or shall I do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I have an option A, an option B.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I can investigate the option A, see the drawbacks of option B. I can look at the drawback.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is kind of secondary to what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to see why are you considering doing either option A or option B, regardless of the results of option A and option B.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you cannot see any drawback in an option A,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still recognize that it's purely rooted in your desire for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You shouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's more important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where the action is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you reflect and contemplate that, the more transparent, in regard to your own motivation, that it's there, while you want to commit the action, you will become.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it will take you less and less effort to see where the action is rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: In greed, aversion, delusion, or non-greed, non-aversion, non-delusion, the more you invest into seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, for a layperson, for example, who is not in the environment of the sensory strain of a monk or somebody who has kind of renounced the world, but who wants to practice the dhamma, so, like, the absolute beginner, so to speak, even that, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to be clear for the reasons, clear about the reasons that are making you act in that direction or in this direction, choosing this, choosing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that applies to any form of action, not just immediate one I'm about to do now, but even my future plans.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as a layperson, I want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I want to practice dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, that's a good answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, where is that suffering that I want to be free from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that suffering in the future?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll practice dhamma in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is that liability to suffering in the present?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's in the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does that liability to suffering in the present manifest to me, really?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, through me experiencing unwanted things through my own actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to practice dhamma in the future, when you get your conditions ready, while in reality, all you need to do is start recognizing where your motivation is rooted, and you'll be practicing dhamma for the same purpose of being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize that... Can you suffer in any way, if you don't want anything?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't want to have anything, and you don't want to keep anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't care about losing anything, or you don't care about gaining anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you experience any discrepancy that would result in suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you then suffer if you don't have any desire whatsoever?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any emotional investment whatsoever?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize, whenever you do suffer, it's because you're emotionally invested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means, whenever you're emotionally invested, means you act out of that as your reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: More pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want a distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want like a nothingness, neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, you're acting out of that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just simply keeping the whole thing going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're sustaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're feeding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the transparency... and again, can you develop transparency in regard to your motivation, if you don't even restrain your actions?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're physically, sort of, already fully rooted in desire and acting towards more desire... Yeah, because those actions are still, you know, that you're keeping... Well, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're fully rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't matter how much you might try to mentally resist.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that you're bodily engaging with with things that are rooted in desire means you you are fully within that cycle.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess, I guess, like, that's the things people... the practice isn't some kind of, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Something that's separate from your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, oh, I just live my life like this and then, all right, now I'll do some practice that's completely got nothing to do with... Basically, if you do practice rightly, it will undermine your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will start undoing your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Undoing your very bhāva, your very being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your life, your life is everything that you're doing, which is determined by your desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the Buddha speaks about the truth and seeing the truth and so on, it's not the truth, you know, a secret.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the truth in regard to your own experience, where my actions are rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can actually recognize what you said earlier on, that there are certain things that are unknown, cannot be known.
[SPEAKER_01]: cannot be empirically, sort of, verified in this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is... Or even, it can be, but not right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, right now, what is empirically verifiable is that these things cannot be empirically verified.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize... and the way... the reason why you can recognize that is because you realize
[SPEAKER_01]: It was never the point of figuring these things out.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point was simply to not maintain greed, aversion, delusion, not maintain desire on the level of body action, speech action, mental action.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you don't have a problem with not knowing things, or haven't figured them long enough, because you you stop assuming that the answer is at the end of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you start to see that, actually, your attempts to try to find out about these things...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already rooted in something, and if you don't ignore that, that's the lacking of truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in, like, lacking of experiencing, like, certain content or certain answers of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean, like, even when people do a meditation technique,
[SPEAKER_01]: That obviously will involve this kind of time and then result of some special experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They remain ignorant of their motivation throughout.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you become aware, you don't need a technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the field where any effort applies.
[SPEAKER_01]: The field of motivation behind me wanted to go retreat, to do this technique, to do that technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is free from suffering for me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it a special... Do I assume it's some sort of experience whereby everything else will be cancelled by it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it something else, perhaps?
[SPEAKER_01]: Have I investigated long enough to see?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... the more... the clearer you are for... about your motives, the clearer you will become about what your goal is as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha talked about the mundane right view, which is recognizing there is good action, there is bad action.
[SPEAKER_01]: That literally means, ah, so there's a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like it... by the way, the action can be same externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a difference whether that action is rooted in absence of desire, absence of greed, aversion, delusion, or is it rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do the same thing externally, it's two different actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you stop judging action by the content, you start seeing it by the motivation behind, which are its necessary, presently enduring roots.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was always struck by the fact that
[SPEAKER_00]: The common sense tells you that you've got an action.
[SPEAKER_00]: We say you're talking about, like, observing an action externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that person is walking over there, and that person is also walking over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're doing the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same action, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same action.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: But they're doing it for different reasons.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's going over there to get away from something, and he's going over there because he wants something, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you distinguish them between the act, the action, the external action, and the motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you're saying is motivation is more important.
[SPEAKER_00]: But actually, the Buddha says the action is the motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not two different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, to talk about the external act is kind of... Well, that's not even an action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why he says cetanā is... Where the action is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what you described is the common sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, common sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not what action is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so... Yeah, every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your intention is your action, even if you don't make a physically discernible, visible by others action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already committed to that action through your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everyone's measure of this external action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is what he does and we can observe externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not what action is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's measuring the results of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's measuring that which is basically rooted in that which is... which is... if you think that's what action is, you're not going to see what action really is, which is the intention that binds it all, like, throughout, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think of the intention as the container of all the acts by body, speech and mind you do within that context of intended, resulting consequence.
[SPEAKER_00]: The example... there's an example that Venerable Jnanavira came up with in his early writings was
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone's drinking a cup of tea and they put a spoonful of sugar into their tea.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're watching this and you know that that's arsenic.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're thinking, why is he killing himself?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... your measure for what it is, this external... what's going on out there... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he doesn't know it's arsonic.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if people are... when people are not aware of their own motivation, then they start assuming motivation of others simply based on the observing of the external acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we spoke about it in other talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where somebody would have unacceptable speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: People just assume ill will and anger and conceit, yet he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will be much more, kind of, prolific in the extent of that, assuming other people's motivation, the more you're unaware of your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you become aware of your own, well, the more accurate in reading other becomes, without needing to assume it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now, you know, you're becoming familiar with how motivation works, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: The action is not what you've done.
[SPEAKER_01]: The action is the intention within which is something you've done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, that's why it's a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because it's already aligning itself with what the right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start recognizing where the work is, where the importance is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start recognizing the criteria for what is wholesome and for what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that criteria for people is external, when they start.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all, you shouldn't do that, you must do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter why.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just must adhere to this form, to this method, to this technique, and then it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can adhere to the technique the rest of your life for completely wrong reasons, and that's why you will not even have a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, the important thing is this mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... it's mundane.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mundane, like, common.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but it's but...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like it doesn't pertain to that universal theorem from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could say there are even... there are people who have no interest in...
[SPEAKER_00]: In dhamma and are closer to the mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are straightforward in their, you know, thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Transparency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because their thinking does not violate the basic principles of that, like, universal nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're looking at what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why am I doing this?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's this?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole... the whole thing, the whole thing of that description of the mundane right view, like, there is given, there's
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in what you observe, but things are rooted in, basically, motivation behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, as I said many times before, certain things, externally done, always have to be rooted in certain intentions, such as killing, stealing, cheating, whatever, sexual intercourse from the point of view of a celibate person, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You abandon that, but everything else is determined by the intention behind, not by the content of what you're doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, there is mother, there is father, there is good, there is bad, there is responsibility for my own actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, oh, responsibility for me walking, sitting, talking, doing this, is on me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the reasoning that I have towards the world, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people say, oh, well, no, I went there because such and such said so, that I should do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might do that, you might choose for that to be the reason for your action, but you will not be able to ignore that you are responsible for choosing that such and such person said something and that was your reason for going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can always say no to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so the the the usual state of affairs is someone
[SPEAKER_00]: I could always say no to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could always say no to the group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is not to, like, go with the group or against the group.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you should always say no to the group.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is to recognize that you're responsible for whatever you choose to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether I say yes or no, it's my choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot abstain from choosing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will then abstain you from responsibility for your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because saying, I will not choose, is your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: My choice is to abstain from choice A and choice B. Oh, so you're responsible for abstaining from choice A and choice B. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why would... why do people then... Avoid responsibility for your choice, because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels a little bit... primordial perfect form of dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha literally means opposite of sukha, means dis-ease or unease.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, you know, suffering and despair of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that uneasiness in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, literally, everything that you experience
[SPEAKER_01]: is of that universal nature of it's not in my control and that's why it makes me uneasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... you have two ways of going about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either pretend it's not there, ignore it, which you can only do as a starting point, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: We all start by ignoring the dukkha, ignoring the universal truth of that nature, which then obviously results in everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The self-view, craving, desire, lust, that then fuels it even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can we say, like, so Sartre would have called that bad faith?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, it's a form of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, literally, you have thing right in front of your face and you pretend it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe that this, that this, it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already your existence, it's already a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe that these things, they were given to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: My feelings have a reason for me, perceptions have a reason for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I believe I have created them by being their master and controller.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you have no say in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still, while not having say in these things you feel, you still maintain the notion that you are the owner of what you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you ignore everything else that would contradict that ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why dukkha cannot enter you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot be liable to it, exposed to it, unless you make yourself so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through ignoring what's obviously there, lack of control, lack of safety, lack of easiness, that's why you become subjected to lack of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you become unsafe and uneasy and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason you ignore it is because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because of that, you experience even more unpleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This great mass of suffering, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, oh, so you have no choice about this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have only choice about how much of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, well, if I actually accept this, which now seems worse, this pleasure of anxiety and uneasiness and lack of control, and endure it, I'm actually overcoming all the other suffering that would be as a result of avoiding this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, even as a mundane right view of a puthujjana, you would be doing... already undoing a lot of... or already removing a lot of dust from your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: A lot of wrong views and other dependencies on greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, suffering is right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Liability to suffering is right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, would you be able to experience any form of suffering, any form of pain, any form of discomfort,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have a desire for anything you gained or anything you lost...
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if the only reason you're giving to desire is to be free from pain, yet desire is the reason for any form of pain, why don't you just abandon the desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus you abandon the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is your goal all along.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: The worst asottava puthujjana, without any inclination to practice the dhamma, and the best, the purest, the greatest of the arahants, same motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be free from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just how they go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to avoid it, or not appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the transparency we talk about, then, is about undoing.
[SPEAKER_01]: These contradictions that you carry already within yourself, they are making you liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about figuring out the truth at the end of your meditation retreat.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would then result in cancellation of all the contradictions and the problems that make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are a lot...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there are lots... there are kind of more... there are grosser types of bad faith that people will... Well, bad faith is as endless as a vijay is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what a vijay is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, someone might...
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to ignore something?
[SPEAKER_01]: To turn a blind eye to it, you need to know that there is at least that thing there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot ignore that which does not exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the weird thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're kind of lying to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how can you lie to yourself because you know... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, that's exactly how... that's why people suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people would suffer on account of what other people say or do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it would remind them of the stuff they're trying to cover up for themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're free from any form of existential cover-up, there is nothing that can provoke you or engage you or affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't crave safety, how could you possibly suffer on account of lack of safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't crave control, if you don't imply control, if you don't assume control, how can you suffer on account of random things happening to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, by the way, when I say control, I don't mean controlling the world or the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, people assume control over their own feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: While, at the same time, simultaneously, they know... they have no say in those feelings arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: They know they're subjected to it, but even that recognition of unsubjected feeling, they put within their assumption of control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They get the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how often the Buddha would ask people who would have approached him like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so you are in control of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which feeling is then in your control?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it pleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the neutral one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there always one of them can only be present, not all of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are in the control of pleasant feeling, how come then it changes into unpleasant one?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're in control of unpleasant, how come it changes into neutral?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you sort of... you can be reminded that, yeah, no, actually, I'm not in control of these feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why people avoid such reminders is because they're unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're trying to outrun discomfort of certain recognitions within yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically you trying to control your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think you are in a position to outrun that which you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're turning a blind eye to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're pretending it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to cover up with a set of feelings you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're kind of living a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what bhāva is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhāva is a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove the contradiction, the existence is ceased.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arahant is contradiction-free.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The transparency begins by acknowledging
[SPEAKER_00]: The contradictions, you know, that, and like you said... By rounding them up, basically, it's a subtler, subtler.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but for most people, I mean, it's just a...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you recognize, what's, what's, what's the first, what would be the most common contradiction of, of, say, a lay person wants to start practicing the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: The contradiction they have to start saying no to.
[SPEAKER_00]: The contradiction they have to start saying no to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, to start rounding it up, start abstaining from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here you are, wanting to develop freedom from suffering, on account of practicing from the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... And I'm still doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to develop, basically, the strength of mind... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...that will be immovable... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...in regard to anything that I might be subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in the meantime, I will keep acting out of my weakness... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...in order to develop strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you want to heal your itchy skin, infected, whatever, ulcers that are really itchy, you have to stop, start scratching and making it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still don't know necessarily what the actual cure might be, but you'd already know you should stop making it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because one thing for sure, even if you find the cure later on, it won't work because you've destroyed your whole arm with your scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already know that certain types of behavior are rooted in being unable to control yourself, unable to restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are, practicing for the ultimate immovability, the ultimate kind of restraint in regard to giving in to pain, giving in to pleasure, giving in to anything that moves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want peace on account of which you keep disturbing yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You basically want to... You're looking for freedom from ill-will and sense desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You give in to your will and sense desire if you want to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're acting out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if both central craving, desire and ill-will were not originally and fundamentally unpleasant, you wouldn't be feeling pressured to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those acts, those experiences are always underlined by that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: By more of that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you know that you are precious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so... Like, you might crave for pleasure, but the only reason you crave for that sensual pleasure is because, simultaneously, underneath it, you crave for freedom from the current.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the context of me is, I don't want this pain of not having that, thus I'll crave for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... what you're craving towards it, it's underlined by even more craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're both simultaneously there, and one feeds the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But looking at this thing that you're heading towards allows you to ignore...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And allows you, like, that hope that that will be the escape of this current pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the sensuality is on the level of assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not getting it, but hoping that getting it will free you from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why sensuality is the assumption, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... Deriving pleasure from sense objects is not what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's assuming that pleasure, simultaneously craving for avoiding the pain of not having it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's on the level of a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first contradiction a layperson has to undo is the contradiction of lack of restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contradiction of not keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a contradiction to your own goal of wanting to practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, ask yourself, like, even if you're not sure... Well, first, you have to be... you have to read the suttas and become familiar with what the actual goal of dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, say, even you're somewhere in between, you're unclear, ask yourself what enlightenment would... what would enlightenment entail for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking, there's so many contradictions you can think of... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that... that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Maintaining contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to make the effort to, oh, I'll keep this contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is ignore it, and that's how you're keeping it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'd say it's quite common, the idea of...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I want to practice for enlightenment, and yet enlightenment is this thing that will happen to me... Out of my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I do these things rightly...
[SPEAKER_01]: If I do this thing here, then something other will suddenly happen to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's already the first thing you should start questioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well...
[SPEAKER_01]: You might want to believe that that's how enlightenment works, but then, if you read the suttas, you realize that's not what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they don't read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, most people probably don't read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I want to practice as the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the Buddha's probably onto something, but I won't find out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't find out.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to practice the Buddha's teaching, but I also don't want to make the effort to find out what that teaching clearly is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just hope that these other people that talk about...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will also prevent you from being clear about your own motives.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start investigating your motives, as I said, your goal will become clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your goal of practicing dhamma is clearer, then it will make obvious sense to invest effort in finding out what that dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you're not there...
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though it's quite a difficult thing to do, there's so many books there, so many things to read, but... Start.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that shouldn't stop me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means like, oh, yeah, okay, so that's the extent of the work that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, it's too much of it, thus I won't do any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... that's just what's... And that's what I've said many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, a person who recognizes what's for his own welfare, as in, whether I engage with
[SPEAKER_01]: Which suffering has greater prospect of resulting in cessation of suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Engaging with sensuality and prolonging desire, or abstaining from it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already didn't have the direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that person would go and find those who teach abstaining from sensuality, to learn more about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he would ponder on what they said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, he would get a sense of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a sense of it, then, he says he measures the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it becomes clearer to him what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you know what needs to be done, he sets to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why people don't know what dhamma practice is, is because they never made the effort to really find out what their task is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, unfortunately, all the effort they made was invested in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people hope that just by listening to this talk on YouTube or that book, that will give me all the knowledge I need.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you ask yourself, what is enlightenment for me?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I think it is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I want enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I want through that enlightenment?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the... what is the sort of... what is the goal of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the result of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it permanent pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Permanent pleasure in what form?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like permanent sensual pleasure or permanent peaceful pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess it's permanent peaceful pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the main characteristic of the permanent peace?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's absence of disturbances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absence of what disturbances?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, absence of disturbances that I know, and see, and hear, and smell, and taste, and touch, and are unable to be indifferent to words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is more likely then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would the perfect peace come as a result of you preventing smell, taste, touch, and all the other senses?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or would perfect peace come as a result of you learning how to be unmoved in regard to smell, sense, and everything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one makes more sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, being unmoved makes more sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why don't I start practicing lack of moving in regard to things right here, right now, that move me?
[SPEAKER_01]: It has... Would that have a greater prospect of pertaining to centrality that you already value through your own random efforts?
[SPEAKER_01]: But now it's not so random anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're actually well-reasoned, well-contemplated, and you're already getting a sense of direction, which means you're already getting a sense of what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what you're doing there is clearer, more transparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't depend on other people and doesn't depend on the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in regard to the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever is to be obtained by oneself, by one's manly effort, manly strength, manly endurance, I obtain.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahantship is something you developed, not something that happens to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it cannot be taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, pleasant feeling has arisen, you're subjected to it, and then it disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you developed your mind in regard to manifestation, in regard to arising of anything, feeling, perception, intention, sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thought, whatever,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dependent on the content of it, but it's dependent on your attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize you will be immovable in regard to anything and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the most extreme examples that are listed in the suttas, will be killed and butchered, and your mind, composure, will not change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's possible, because your practice has ceased to pertain to the circumstances, to the senses, but it started looking at the nature of it, in regard to which you train your immovability, imperturbability.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that training starts when you're completely unenlightened, patujana.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't, you don't magically slot into it, when you develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop the right view, because you've been training rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you say,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's quite common to, I think, for people to think that practicing the dhamma involves... not thinking, involves kind of... thinking... Just do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're overthinking these things, just... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the question you should immediately ask yourself there is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's just about doing it, where is the motivation for doing rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it rooted in doing, or is it rooted in thought behind your doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are ignoring thought on account of your doing, means you ignore the reason for motivation, which means you ignore what action is, and somehow you're hoping to free yourself from action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, if someone wants to really start practicing in line with the dhamma, if they're not already, which you probably are if you're listening to these videos, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about, kind of, you know, I do need to start thinking about my motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where dhamma is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: My motivation for it...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not justified in doing anything or not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no justification for anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever I do or whatever I choose not to do, it's because I made a choice for which I'm responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I'm not justified or absolved from that responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, because I want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's important is my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm responsible for what's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, recognizing that responsibility, not running away from it, not covering it up because it's unpleasant, accepting that uneasiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're responsible, yet you're not in control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a very uneasy situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, if I tell you, oh, if something happens to such and such person, if they do something stupid, you pay the price.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not at fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what existence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good way of putting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to recognize... recognizing that existential responsibility is the gateway for the direction of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can spend 50 years practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you haven't started that practice through that gateway, there is no dhamma in your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that upsets you, hearing that, well, it just confirms that you haven't developed freedom from suffering, you haven't developed imperturbability in regard to circumstances, which is words of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is my practice freeing me from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by controlling the circumstances, preventing the exposure to things they might have said to me, but through me being unable to move, unable to suffer, unable to despair, on account of things I cannot escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you will not need an escape anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in trying to outrun saṃsāṃs, mādhya-sthācchas, deny them through refusing to think about them, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot suffer either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's truly the burdenless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no burden for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I see this, I must do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I think that, I must run this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you say that's the kind of... that sense of self is almost... that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Safety...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a product.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of your dependence on looking for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the assumption that there is some... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the direct product.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Self is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you want to approve that symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you stop maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop ignoring saṅkhara.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being the dukkha and being anicca and being dukkha, as in being not in my control and being uneasy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop ignoring non-control and uneasiness, you will stop maintaining, this is mine, this is myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily think about, oh, now I must practice anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta will be the result of you not supporting atta, through your own actions and thinking and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, start undoing contradictions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will result in the right view, and then that will result in arhantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the fundamental contradiction, sorry, is what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't need to chase down all the contradictions in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Start with the ones that are, like, more obvious to you, based on whatever faculties you have, but fundamentally, bring them all home, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the fundamental contradiction of this body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that I assume control over it, and yet I'm not in control of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you assume... and, like, the life that depends upon the operating body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can that be in your control?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, is that... is that the context that you have at the back of your mind throughout your day?
[SPEAKER_01]: That you're not in control on your own body, let alone of your own life?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is that a context that you kind of drift away from and forget about and ignore?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to make extra effort towards ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is ignore the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you're investing in ignorance already.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you need to do is lose the sight of the context that you're not in control of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you lose that sight, automatically, you're assuming control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Automatically, you're acting out of greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's learning not to tolerate contradictions, but also learning to recognize them, because you've, for so long, you've allowed them to be there without actually... And you will recognize them when you learn how to endure them, and not give in to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you learn to endure the uneasiness,
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, the first uneasiness you're going to get is the uneasiness of starting to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you might... you might, first of all, that those contradictions might be gross, might be quite obvious, but maybe that's why you need to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you're saying is like, well, there will be more deep-rooted... And if you wonder where the contradictions are, well, just ask yourself, have you been acting out of desire recently?
[SPEAKER_01]: Have you committed any act by body, speech or mind out of desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's your contradiction already.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire implies ownership, implies that result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you feel the shame?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see the danger of that design?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another contradiction, because it's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here you are, riding on this body, as if you created it, you're in control, yet you have no idea even how components operate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if something interferes with it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your ride is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's finished.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why death is so terrifying for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because death is terrifying itself, but because you literally, your entire existence, ignores it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you ignore it, the more power it has.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that transparency is developed sufficiently enough, then, literally, it becomes obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpatti is obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the declaration of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature to manifest, for that very reason, it's not in my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you just cultivate that same thing and any traces of any desire, any little contradictions or discrepancies, gone.